<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Drupalcon | Oh The Huge Manatee]]></title>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/categories/drupalcon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-29T16:58:17+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Campbell Vertesi (ohthehugemanatee)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why No Mainstream PHP Speakers Come to Drupalcon - and How We're Changing That]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2017/07/29/bring-php-to-drupalcon/"/>
    <updated>2017-07-29T17:01:59+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2017/07/29/bring-php-to-drupalcon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve learned something incredible as the PHP Track Chair for Drupalcon Vienna. <strong>The Drupal Association has no way to invite PHP speakers to Drupalcon</strong>.</p>

<p>This blew me away when I first learned about it. After all the work to bring mainstream PHP to Drupal core, after all the outreach to <a href="https://php-fig.org">PHP-FIG</a>, after all the talks Drupalists have given at major PHP conferences, how is this possible?</p>

<p>You see, <strong>basically every other PHP conference covers their speakers' travel and accommodation costs</strong>. Drupalcon doesn&rsquo;t, and never has. Historically it has to do with Drupalcon&rsquo;s identity as a community conference, rather than a professional one. But it means <strong>the best PHP speakers never get to Drupalcon</strong>.</p>

<p>On one hand that&rsquo;s great for our project: our speakers are all passionate volunteers! They&rsquo;re specialists who care deeply about the project. On the other hand, it contributes to isolated, &ldquo;stay on the island&rdquo; thinking. If the only speakers we hear are Drupalists, where do we get new insights? If the only people at the BoF or code sprint table are Drupalists, how do we leverage the strengths of the broader PHP community? How do we contribute back? <em>How do we grow?</em></p>

<p>Every year, the lack of financial support holds back major PHP contributors from speaking at Drupalcon. The maintainers of Composer, PHPUnit, and Guzzle <em>want</em> to come to Drupalcon, but we don&rsquo;t make it possible. <strong>These people built and maintain the cornerstones of Drupal. Why do we hold them at arm&rsquo;s length?</strong></p>

<p>This year, as Drupalcon PHP Track Chair, I&rsquo;m in a position to make some changes. So I invited two notable PHP speakers to come and join us at the con: <strong>Sebastian Bergmann, author of PHPUnit</strong>, and <strong>Michelle Sanver, president of @phpwomen</strong>. Today I&rsquo;m announcing a very special <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/php-at-drupalcon">GoFundMe campaign</a> to pay the travel and accommodation for these two exceptional contributors.</p>

<iframe class='gfm-media-widget' image='1' coinfo='0' width='100%' height='100%' frameborder='0' id='php-at-drupalcon'></iframe>


<script src='http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io//funds.gofundme.com/js/5.0/media-widget.js'></script>


<br />


<p>I believe that Drupalists want to get off the island.</p>

<p>I believe in the benefits of closer cooperation with the PHP community.</p>

<p>I believe there&rsquo;s a lot we can learn from these people, and a lot we can teach them too.</p>

<p><strong>And I believe that I&rsquo;m not the only one.</strong></p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve estimated costs conservatively; this is not a lot of money. Anything we collect above and beyond their needs will go to the Drupal Association, but let&rsquo;s be honest with ourselves: this campaign isn&rsquo;t just about bringing Sebastian and Michelle to Drupalcon. <strong>Your donation shows the Drupal Association that you want to welcome contributors from other communities.</strong> You prove to them that their constituents <em>want</em> to bring in this kind of speaker. <strong>When you donate, you stand up for the kind of community you believe in.</strong></p>

<p>Please <a href="https://www.gofundme.com/php-at-drupalcon/donate">donate</a>, share, and tweet the campaign today.</p>

<iframe class='gfm-media-widget' image='0' coinfo='0' width='100%' height='100%' frameborder='0' id='php-at-drupalcon'></iframe>


<script src='http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io//funds.gofundme.com/js/5.0/media-widget.js'></script>


<br />


<p><strong>Because &ldquo;get off the island&rdquo; isn&rsquo;t just about the code. It&rsquo;s about the community.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better PHP === Better Drupalists: The PHP Track at Drupalcon Vienna]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2017/06/15/better-php-better-drupalists/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-15T17:19:24+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2017/06/15/better-php-better-drupalists</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the best parts of Drupal 8 is our shift to enterprise PHP coding structures. With tools like composer and Symfony&rsquo;s structures like Events and Dependency Injection, Drupalists are learning to be great PHP developers, and vice-versa. Today, the fastest route to becoming a rock star Drupalist is through PHP.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m one of the PHP track chairs for Drupalcon Vienna, and this year our focus is <em>better PHP === better Drupalists</em>. How can better PHP make your life as a Drupal developer easier?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p><strong>Do you like PHP 7?</strong> We want to hear about the technicalities of types, throwing all the things, and your favorite operators (mine is null coalesce, but full respect for you spaceship operator fans).</p>

<p><strong>Have you seen the light of functional programming?</strong> Tell us why we should love higher orders with lambda functions and closures. Let&rsquo;s hear the finer points of first class functions.</p>

<p><strong>Do your tests bring all the bugs to the yard?</strong> We want to talk about it. Every method is a promise, and your tests make sure you keep your promises. We want sessions about test driven development in a drupal context, choosing the right test framework and scope, and how your real-world tests are saving you real-world time.</p>

<p><strong>Have you written a composer library wrapper module yet?</strong> Submit a session about how composer is saving you lines of code.</p>

<p><strong>Is your development environment fine-tuned for drupal excellence?</strong> Tell us how, and why.</p>

<p>We have only two weeks left until session submissions close! <a href="https://events.drupal.org/node/add/session?og_group_ref=14447">Get your session in now</a> and help us make Drupal code something to be proud of.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coder vs. Themer Ultimate Grudge Match Smackdown Fight to the Death]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2014/05/01/coder-vs-themer-ultimate-grudge-match-smackdown-fight-to-the-death/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-01T17:15:31+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2014/05/01/coder-vs-themer-ultimate-grudge-match-smackdown-fight-to-the-death</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m really excited about a new session that I&rsquo;ve been doing with my friend and colleague, <a href="https://twitter.com/adamjurantenor">Adam Juran aka scaragucc</a>: the Coder vs Themer Ultimate Grudge Match Smackdown Fight to the Death! The basic premise: we both start with the same wireframe of a front page to build. But <em>I&rsquo;m only allowed to use the module layer, and Adam is only allowed to use the theme layer</em>. It&rsquo;s a really fun and entertaining way to play with the blurry lines between &ldquo;coder&rdquo; and &ldquo;themer&rdquo;. We get the audience pretty pumped up, which is impressive for a session that&rsquo;s basically about watching other people code!</p>

<p>If you didn&rsquo;t catch it at <a href="http://szeged2014.drupaldays.org/program/sessions/themer-vs-coder-ultimate-grudge-smackdown-fight-death">Drupal Dev Days in Szeged</a>, or at <a href="https://2014.drupalcamp-frankfurt.de/session/themer-vs-coder-ultimate-grudge-smackdown-fight-death">Drupalcamp Frankfurt</a>, you&rsquo;re probably going to have to wait for Drupalcon Amsterdam to take part! But I do have a video of the session at Frankfurt, just to whet your appetite. :)</p>

<iframe width="768" height="432" src="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Rly9D3-gc4w" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>You can consider this a challenge: if any other themers out there want to challenge me to a coder vs themer style battle, I&rsquo;ll be keynoting at <a href="http://drupalcamp.fi">Drupalcamp Helsinki</a> in a few weeks. I&rsquo;ll meet you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
