<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Drupalcon | Oh The Huge Manatee]]></title>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/categories/drupalcon/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-06-15T17:23:47+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Campbell Vertesi (ohthehugemanatee)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better PHP === Better Drupalists: The PHP Track at Drupalcon Vienna]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2017/06/15/better-php-better-drupalists/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-15T17:19:24+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2017/06/15/better-php-better-drupalists</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the best parts of Drupal 8 is our shift to enterprise PHP coding structures. With tools like composer and Symfony&rsquo;s structures like Events and Dependency Injection, Drupalists are learning to be great PHP developers, and vice-versa. Today, the fastest route to becoming a rock star Drupalist is through PHP.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m one of the PHP track chairs for Drupalcon Vienna, and this year our focus is <em>better PHP === better Drupalists</em>. How can better PHP make your life as a Drupal developer easier?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p></p>

<p><strong>Do you like PHP 7?</strong> We want to hear about the technicalities of types, throwing all the things, and your favorite operators (mine is null coalesce, but full respect for you spaceship operator fans).</p>

<p><strong>Have you seen the light of functional programming?</strong> Tell us why we should love higher orders with lambda functions and closures. Let&rsquo;s hear the finer points of first class functions.</p>

<p><strong>Do your tests bring all the bugs to the yard?</strong> We want to talk about it. Every method is a promise, and your tests make sure you keep your promises. We want sessions about test driven development in a drupal context, choosing the right test framework and scope, and how your real-world tests are saving you real-world time.</p>

<p><strong>Have you written a composer library wrapper module yet?</strong> Submit a session about how composer is saving you lines of code.</p>

<p><strong>Is your development environment fine-tuned for drupal excellence?</strong> Tell us how, and why.</p>

<p>We have only two weeks left until session submissions close! <a href="https://events.drupal.org/node/add/session?og_group_ref=14447">Get your session in now</a> and help us make Drupal code something to be proud of.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coder vs. Themer Ultimate Grudge Match Smackdown Fight to the Death]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2014/05/01/coder-vs-themer-ultimate-grudge-match-smackdown-fight-to-the-death/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-01T17:15:31+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io/blog/2014/05/01/coder-vs-themer-ultimate-grudge-match-smackdown-fight-to-the-death</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m really excited about a new session that I&rsquo;ve been doing with my friend and colleague, <a href="https://twitter.com/adamjurantenor">Adam Juran aka scaragucc</a>: the Coder vs Themer Ultimate Grudge Match Smackdown Fight to the Death! The basic premise: we both start with the same wireframe of a front page to build. But <em>I&rsquo;m only allowed to use the module layer, and Adam is only allowed to use the theme layer</em>. It&rsquo;s a really fun and entertaining way to play with the blurry lines between &ldquo;coder&rdquo; and &ldquo;themer&rdquo;. We get the audience pretty pumped up, which is impressive for a session that&rsquo;s basically about watching other people code!</p>

<p>If you didn&rsquo;t catch it at <a href="http://szeged2014.drupaldays.org/program/sessions/themer-vs-coder-ultimate-grudge-smackdown-fight-death">Drupal Dev Days in Szeged</a>, or at <a href="https://2014.drupalcamp-frankfurt.de/session/themer-vs-coder-ultimate-grudge-smackdown-fight-death">Drupalcamp Frankfurt</a>, you&rsquo;re probably going to have to wait for Drupalcon Amsterdam to take part! But I do have a video of the session at Frankfurt, just to whet your appetite. :)</p>

<iframe width="768" height="432" src="http://ohthehugemanatee.github.io//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Rly9D3-gc4w" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>You can consider this a challenge: if any other themers out there want to challenge me to a coder vs themer style battle, I&rsquo;ll be keynoting at <a href="http://drupalcamp.fi">Drupalcamp Helsinki</a> in a few weeks. I&rsquo;ll meet you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
