<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Android | Oh, The Huge Manatee]]></title>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/categories/android/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/"/>
  <updated>2019-02-11T14:31:05+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Campbell Vertesi (ohthehugemanatee)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Troubleshooting Android Error -505 From Google Play]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2015/05/29/troubleshooting-android-error-505-from-google-play/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-29T12:20:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2015/05/29/troubleshooting-android-error-505-from-google-play</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently got a new Android phone, and very quickly had trouble installing some of my favorite apps. Google&rsquo;s Play Store downloads the app successfully, then presents me with &ldquo;Unknown Error -505&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/error-505.jpg" title="&ldquo;Error 505&rdquo;" ></p>

<p>This error message means precisely nothing. It means &ldquo;something went wrong during installation, and we&rsquo;re not telling you what.&rdquo; This drives me crazy. This blog post is about how to get more information out of that error message, and how to fix the problem.</p>

<p>Your device is not going to give you more information on its own. Instead, you need to install ADB, the &ldquo;Android Debug Bridge&rdquo; which lets you type commands directly to your Android device over a USB connection. It&rsquo;s not hard to install, so <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/?q=how+to+install+adb">go and set that up now</a>.</p>

<p>Next, you will have to make sure your Android device permits you to use ADB. On the phone, go to Settings > About Phone, and scroll down to where you see &ldquo;Build Number&rdquo; listed. Tap on &ldquo;Build Number&rdquo; until you see a popup telling you that you are now a &ldquo;developer&rdquo;. Then go back to Settings, and tap on the new &ldquo;Developer Options&rdquo; menu item near the bottom. Enable the &ldquo;USB Debugging&rdquo; option there.</p>

<p>Now plug your phone into your computer via USB, and open up your Terminal. Windows users, use the Console &ndash; it&rsquo;s the same thing. First, we&rsquo;ll see if our Android device is even visible to ADB.</p>

<p><code>bash
$&gt; adb devices
</code></p>

<p>You should see a list of devices attached, with (probably) only one listing. If not, check to make sure that your phone is really in USB Debugging mode.</p>

<p>Now, we&rsquo;re going to try to install that same troublesome application over ADB. In order to do this, you&rsquo;ll have to download the application&rsquo;s installer (APK) file on your computer. Google makes this hard to do directly, you&rsquo;ll have to use a <a href="http://apps.evozi.com/apk-downloader/">third-party website</a> or a <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-us/firefox/addon/apk-downloader/?src=search">browser extension</a> to find your download link. Download that APK file and save it somewhere safe on your computer. Remember the path to that file! I saved mine in <em>~/Downloads</em>.</p>

<p>With that APK file in hand, let&rsquo;s try installing your application over ADB. My problematic app was the Deutsche Bahn Navigator app, but obviously you should substitute the filename to your APK here.</p>

<p><code>bash
$&gt; adb install ~/Downloads/de.hafas.android.db.apk
5051 KB/s (5991578 bytes in 1.158s)
  pkg: /data/local/tmp/de.hafas.android.db.apk
Failure [INSTALL_FAILED_DUPLICATE_PERMISSION perm=de.dbnavigator.permission.list pkg=de.bahn.dbtickets]
</code></p>

<p>(Full disclosure: that is not the exact permission and package I had, I foolishly closed the terminal window before recording it. But the error and the format are correct, which is what&rsquo;s important here.)</p>

<p>NOW we have something to work with! We get an error message, and some information that might explain what&rsquo;s going on. In this case, the installation failed because of a duplicate permission, whatever that means. But it tells me the name of the permission, and &ndash; even better &ndash; the package that controls it. Notice that com.dbtickets is not the application I was trying to install. It&rsquo;s something else, a separate app I had, called &ldquo;DB Tickets&rdquo;. This tells me that if I uninstall that other application, it should solve this problem. You can do that from ADB as well:</p>

<p>``` bash
$> adb uninstall de.bahn.dbtickets
Success</p>

<p>```</p>

<p>Now I can try installing the original app again, and it should work. I can do that from the Play Store application, or directly from ADB with the command we tried above. At this point, I&rsquo;m way more likely to try it through ADB just to make sure I get an error message if it breaks!</p>

<p>You can follow this process to get further information about any error -505 you may receive. You can do all sorts of things through ADB to resolve this kind of problem. Check the <a href="https://developer.android.com/tools/help/adb.html#commandsummary">complete list of commands</a> for more information.</p>

<h2>Postlude</h2>

<p>This experience pointed out two large Ux failures on the part of Google:</p>

<p>First, is one of the most frustrating Ux concepts out there, which I call: &ldquo;never present the user with useful information.&rdquo; I understand that 99% of the time, users do not want or need to see technical information about what&rsquo;s going on. Even <em>I</em> want my systems to seem like they &ldquo;just work.&rdquo; But the 1% of the time when we DO want technical information, is in our error messages. The sensible Ux policy to adopt here, is &ldquo;make every error message easy to google for more information&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Second, enabling developer mode. Here are the official instructions:</p>

<blockquote><p>&hellip;go to Settings > About phone and tap Build number seven times. Return to the previous screen to find Developer options at the bottom.</p></blockquote>

<p>&hellip; what? This is 2015. You don&rsquo;t have to hide your &ldquo;Developer mode&rdquo; behind some obscure Easter Egg behavior. I don&rsquo;t know if it&rsquo;s standard, but on my phone you&rsquo;re asked right at the start what level of settings you want to see: simple or advanced. Adding a third level for &ldquo;developer&rdquo; would make a lot more sense.</p>

<p>But hey, at least we can always get what we want from the terminal.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
