<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Politics | Oh, The Huge Manatee]]></title>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/categories/politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/"/>
  <updated>2019-10-08T20:29:47+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Campbell Vertesi (ohthehugemanatee)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chinese Censorship, Values Decisions, and Free Software]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2019/10/08/chinese-censorship-and-free-software/"/>
    <updated>2019-10-08T19:10:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2019/10/08/chinese-censorship-and-free-software</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Chinese censors are in the news this weekend: <a href="https://variety.com/2019/gaming/news/blizzard-bans-blitzchung-hearthstone-hong-kong-china-statement-1203363050/">Blizzard banned a grandmaster Hearthstone player for supporting Hong Kong in an interview</a>, <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/south-park-band-china-why-banned-china-s23-e02-23x02-1463762">South Park was added to the &ldquo;banned&rdquo; list for their critique of Chinese censorship in Hollywood</a>, and <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/10/07/business/houston-rockets-nba-china-daryl-morey/index.html">an NBA franchise owner&rsquo;s job was on the line for a pro-HK tweet</a>. Increasingly, Western companies are finding themselves up against the wall to prioritize western liberal values against access to the enormous Chinese market. We can imagine the difficult, high-pressure decisions for executives in this situation.</p>

<p>As a consumer it feels like we don&rsquo;t face that kind of pressure, or that kind of decision. Those of us whose choices do not impact thousands of employees' livelihoods, and millions of consumers' information environments, seem to have little leverage. If <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/sep/25/revealed-how-tiktok-censors-videos-that-do-not-please-beijing">TikTok quietly hides any videos of Hong Kong unrest</a>, or <a href="https://sputniknews.com/asia/201801121060701327-china-delta-apology-taiwan-tibet/">Delta lists Taiwan as a part of China</a>, or <a href="https://mothership.sg/2018/01/marriott-zara-qantas-taiwan-tibet-sovereignty/">Marriott includes cities in Tibet, Taiwan, Hong Kong, and Macau as inside China</a>&hellip; we can&rsquo;t tell the difference. The whole point of censorship is that you remain blissfully unaware of what you&rsquo;re missing.</p>

<p>When we as consumers think about China&rsquo;s censorship power in our lives the important question is: <em>How can we tell when it&rsquo;s happening</em>? It&rsquo;s not unthinkable for Chrome to invisibly hide certain content, or Facebook, or your iPhone. In fact most of the information services you use likely do this already, in the name of curating content you will &ldquo;like.&rdquo; This isn&rsquo;t necessarily a problem in and of itself; it only gets problematic when the filters are <em>invisible</em>.</p>

<p>This is a part of the point of Free and Open Source software. Filters can&rsquo;t be applied in secret, and by definition you have the right to fork software to do things <em>your</em> way if you like. It&rsquo;s <em>your</em> right to have <em>your</em> device behave the way <em>you</em> want it to. And black boxes should inspire some suspicion that they may be doing things you don&rsquo;t like.</p>

<p>At this point it would be easy to descend into the typical open source rant: if only Facebook open sourced its filters! If only Instagram were open! I&rsquo;ll leave that for others. I want to point out something a little subtler:</p>

<p>The executive&rsquo;s values decision about western liberalism vs a larger addressable market, is remarkably close to the developer&rsquo;s values decision about a license that respects user control vs the easier monetization and control of a black box. That decision in turn is related to the consumer&rsquo;s values decision, about software that respects your rights vs the convenience of a popular black box.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s easy to criticize Blizzard&rsquo;s decision to bow to Chinese sensibilities. But how do <em>you</em> decide, on your own much smaller scale? Do <em>you</em> prioritize values over convenience? Or do you accept the censored experience of a black box as a user? Do you enjoy the control of that black box as a developer?</p>

<p>Hearthstone players are by definition running a black box OS. Users of iOS, Windows, and Android demonstrate comfort with invisible censors in other parts of their devices. Is their presence in video streams and gameplay all that different? Do they have any right to complain? Having given away control to black boxes, perhaps complaining is the way they can impact the way their device runs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Open Letter to My MEPs About Article 17 (Formerly Article 13)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2019/03/21/an-open-letter-to-my-meps-about-article-17-formerly-article-13/"/>
    <updated>2019-03-21T23:44:43+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2019/03/21/an-open-letter-to-my-meps-about-article-17-formerly-article-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The proposal for a directive on copyright in the digital single market is disastrous for the <strong>EU economy, culture, and democracy in the digital world</strong>. It is particularly bad for my country of Germany, as a leading light in Europe in all three areas. I am writing all of my MEPs listed in support of this impossibly bad proposal.</p>

<p>The German and European economies would be terribly damaged by this article, which <strong>effectively rules out small and medium sized competition in favor of the largest incumbents</strong>. I work for Microsoft on precisely the kind of machine-understanding tasks involved in the copyright filter requirement. I can tell you with authority: <strong>it is an impossible task which only the deepest pockets can approach</strong>. <strong>Article 17 makes Germany and Europe into hostile venues for Internet startups</strong>. The next generation of Youtubes, Soundclouds, and Netflixes are not possible under this Article &ndash; unless of course, it&rsquo;s an existing mega-corporation who decides to start it. <strong>This is a tremendous handicap in the fastest growing sector of the global economy.</strong></p>

<p>The disaster for culture exemplifies the impossibility of such a filter. My &ldquo;side business&rdquo; is an entertainment company, making opera music accessible for tens of thousands of Europeans every year. The entire classical music industry opposes digital filters because we all know the consequence: <strong>a machine or untrained human can&rsquo;t tell the difference between the 300 different versions of Bach&rsquo;s Wohl Temperierte Klavier</strong>. The piece is identified as probably copyrighted because copyrighted versions exist, and taken down as a precaution. <strong>Famously even the European anthem, <em>An die Freude</em>, suffers automated takedowns</strong> because there are copyrighted versions of the piece. <strong>Asking platforms to bulk-police content means that the more influential a piece of music is for our culture &ndash; that is to say, the more versions of it exist &ndash; the more prone it is to spurious blocking on copyright grounds.</strong></p>

<p>As much as the technical infeasibility and halting the spread of the most important pieces of our European culture bother me,<strong> the effect on democracy in the digital age is the worst part of this Article. User-generated content is foundational to online discussion</strong>. It is precisely this content which enriches online debate and engagement, which reaches younger generations and pulls them into a very participatory democratic environment. You&rsquo;ve no doubt heard that <strong>memes are culture</strong>, but <strong>they are also the medium of exchange in the biggest democratic commons humankind has ever created</strong>. Legislation which shuts down this medium of exchange, or which forces the commons into channels controlled by the largest (foreign) economic actors in history, is bad for the EU.</p>

<p><strong>Perhaps the world needs a digital copyright equivalent of Brexit</strong>, to scare everyone else away from the copyright lobby. Perhaps we all need a material example to see just how poorly the copyright lobby&rsquo;s 1960&rsquo;s-era ideology fits the 21st century economy.</p>

<p><strong>But I would prefer it not be my country, my continent that makes an example of itself.</strong></p>

<p>Please heed <a href="https://saveyourinternet.eu/statements/">the warnings from internet experts, the UN Special Rapporteur on Freedom of Expression, NGOs, programmers, and academics</a>. I urge you to reconsider your position on this digital Brexit.</p>

<p>Sincerely,</p>

<p>Campbell Vertesi</p>

<p>Berlin, Germany</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Net Neutrality and Steve Wozniak]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/2010/12/net-neutrality-and-steve-wozniak.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-22T00:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/2010/12/net-neutrality-and-steve-wozniak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p>

<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
I know no one reads this blog but me, but I may as well put this up here. &nbsp;Net Neutrality: I'm for it.<br /><br />Steve Wozniak has an excellent <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2010/12/an-open-letter-to-the-fcc-regarding-net-neutrality/68294/">Open Letter</a> up on the Atlantic about the issue. &nbsp;He takes the examples of public goods such as roadworks and compares them favorably to privately managed utilities like Cable TV and Internet. <br /><br />Personally, I think his letter is a much more effective critique of the FCC than it is a championing of the public works model of construction. &nbsp;After all, it's the FCC that regulates the cable and telephone industries so ineffectively. &nbsp;And the very road system he proclaims as being so effective was a famous example of political favor outweighing practicality when the road system was devised in the 19th Century. <br /><br />In this case though, I think we have a free and open marketplace of ideas by explicit design in the Internet. &nbsp;It is trivially simple to create rules to preserve this. We should.
</div>


<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
