<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Politics | Oh, The Huge Manatee]]></title>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/categories/politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/"/>
  <updated>2019-03-21T23:59:51+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Campbell Vertesi (ohthehugemanatee)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Open Letter to My MEPs About Article 17 (Formerly Article 13)]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2019/03/21/an-open-letter-to-my-meps-about-article-17-formerly-article-13/"/>
    <updated>2019-03-21T23:44:43+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2019/03/21/an-open-letter-to-my-meps-about-article-17-formerly-article-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The proposal for a directive on copyright in the digital single market is disastrous for the <strong>EU economy, culture, and democracy in the digital world</strong>. It is particularly bad for my country of Germany, as a leading light in Europe in all three areas. I am writing all of my MEPs listed in support of this impossibly bad proposal.</p>

<p>The German and European economies would be terribly damaged by this article, which <strong>effectively rules out small and medium sized competition in favor of the largest incumbents</strong>. I work for Microsoft on precisely the kind of machine-understanding tasks involved in the copyright filter requirement. I can tell you with authority: <strong>it is an impossible task which only the deepest pockets can approach</strong>. <strong>Article 17 makes Germany and Europe into hostile venues for Internet startups</strong>. The next generation of Youtubes, Soundclouds, and Netflixes are not possible under this Article &ndash; unless of course, it&rsquo;s an existing mega-corporation who decides to start it. <strong>This is a tremendous handicap in the fastest growing sector of the global economy.</strong></p>

<p>The disaster for culture exemplifies the impossibility of such a filter. My &ldquo;side business&rdquo; is an entertainment company, making opera music accessible for tens of thousands of Europeans every year. The entire classical music industry opposes digital filters because we all know the consequence: <strong>a machine or untrained human can&rsquo;t tell the difference between the 300 different versions of Bach&rsquo;s Wohl Temperierte Klavier</strong>. The piece is identified as probably copyrighted because copyrighted versions exist, and taken down as a precaution. <strong>Famously even the European anthem, <em>An die Freude</em>, suffers automated takedowns</strong> because there are copyrighted versions of the piece. <strong>Asking platforms to bulk-police content means that the more influential a piece of music is for our culture &ndash; that is to say, the more versions of it exist &ndash; the more prone it is to spurious blocking on copyright grounds.</strong></p>

<p>As much as the technical infeasibility and halting the spread of the most important pieces of our European culture bother me,<strong> the effect on democracy in the digital age is the worst part of this Article. User-generated content is foundational to online discussion</strong>. It is precisely this content which enriches online debate and engagement, which reaches younger generations and pulls them into a very participatory democratic environment. You&rsquo;ve no doubt heard that <strong>memes are culture</strong>, but <strong>they are also the medium of exchange in the biggest democratic commons humankind has ever created</strong>. Legislation which shuts down this medium of exchange, or which forces the commons into channels controlled by the largest (foreign) economic actors in history, is bad for the EU.</p>

<p><strong>Perhaps the world needs a digital copyright equivalent of Brexit</strong>, to scare everyone else away from the copyright lobby. Perhaps we all need a material example to see just how poorly the copyright lobby&rsquo;s 1960&rsquo;s-era ideology fits the 21st century economy.</p>

<p><strong>But I would prefer it not be my country, my continent that makes an example of itself.</strong></p>

<p>Please heed <a href="https://saveyourinternet.eu/statements/">the warnings from internet experts, the UN Special Rapporteur on Freedom of Expression, NGOs, programmers, and academics</a>. I urge you to reconsider your position on this digital Brexit.</p>

<p>Sincerely,</p>

<p>Campbell Vertesi</p>

<p>Berlin, Germany</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Net Neutrality and Steve Wozniak]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/2010/12/net-neutrality-and-steve-wozniak.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-22T00:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/2010/12/net-neutrality-and-steve-wozniak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p>

<div class="css-full-post-content js-full-post-content">
I know no one reads this blog but me, but I may as well put this up here. &nbsp;Net Neutrality: I'm for it.<br /><br />Steve Wozniak has an excellent <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2010/12/an-open-letter-to-the-fcc-regarding-net-neutrality/68294/">Open Letter</a> up on the Atlantic about the issue. &nbsp;He takes the examples of public goods such as roadworks and compares them favorably to privately managed utilities like Cable TV and Internet. <br /><br />Personally, I think his letter is a much more effective critique of the FCC than it is a championing of the public works model of construction. &nbsp;After all, it's the FCC that regulates the cable and telephone industries so ineffectively. &nbsp;And the very road system he proclaims as being so effective was a famous example of political favor outweighing practicality when the road system was devised in the 19th Century. <br /><br />In this case though, I think we have a free and open marketplace of ideas by explicit design in the Internet. &nbsp;It is trivially simple to create rules to preserve this. We should.
</div>


<p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
