<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Linux | Oh, The Huge Manatee]]></title>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/categories/linux/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-07T12:58:17+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Campbell Vertesi (ohthehugemanatee)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BTRFS Out of Space Emergency Response]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2019/01/04/btrfs-out-of-space-emergency-response/"/>
    <updated>2019-01-04T13:58:39+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2019/01/04/btrfs-out-of-space-emergency-response</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I run BTRFS on my root filesystem (on Linux), mostly for the quick snapshot and restore functionality. Yesterday I ran into a common problem: my drive was suddenly full. I went from 4GB of free space to 0 in an instant, causing all sorts of chaos on my system.</p>

<p>This problem happens to lots of people, beause BTRFS doesn&rsquo;t have a linear relationship to &ldquo;free space available&rdquo;. There are a few concepts that get in the way:</p>

<ul>
<li>Compression: BTRFS supports compressing data as it writes. This obviously changes the amount of data that can be stored. &ndash; 50MB of text may take only 5MB &ldquo;room&rdquo; on the drive.</li>
<li>Metadata: BTRFS stores your data separately from metadata. Both data and metadata occupy &ldquo;space&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Multiple devices: BTRFS supports multiple devices working together, RAID-style. That means there&rsquo;s extra information to store for every file. For example, RAID-1 stores two copies of every file, so a 50MB file takes 100MB of space.</li>
<li>Nested volumes: BTRFS lets you divide the filesystem into &ldquo;subvolumes&rdquo; &ndash; each of which can (someday) have its own RAID configuration.</li>
</ul>


<p>It&rsquo;s easy to look at the drive and tell how many MiB of space has not been used yet. But it&rsquo;s very hard to accurately say how much of your data you can write in that space! For this reason the amount of &ldquo;free space&rdquo; reported on BRFS volumes by system utilities like <code>df</code> can jump a lot &ndash; like my disappearing 4GiB.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The #1 Question I Get Asked Working at MS: Why Do You Run Linux?]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2018/02/07/the-number-1-question-i-get-asked-working-at-msy-do-you-run-linux/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-07T16:42:50+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2018/02/07/the-number-1-question-i-get-asked-working-at-msy-do-you-run-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve had all of a week working at Microsoft, and so far it&rsquo;s been great. I&rsquo;ve managed to get my Linux daily driver machine working with almost all the MS internal systems (more on that in a separate post), and all the daily use applications have web or Linux versions available. So far, so good!</p>




<p><img class="center" src="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/images/ms-loves-linux.png" title="I see this banner all over the MS Intranet" ></p>




<p>But every time I&rsquo;ve asked for support, or visited IT, or encountered something that didn&rsquo;t work perfectly, I hear the same question: &ldquo;Why do you want to run open source software, anyway?&rdquo;  The question isn&rsquo;t asked with malice or condescention. It&rsquo;s asked with genuine curiosity. This is tremendous progress for Microsoft.</p>




<p>It is an important question, though: Why do I run Linux? Especially when it&rsquo;s not explicitly supported, when it entails more work, or more frustration. Why put myself through that?</p>




<p>First of all, it&rsquo;s none of your business what I run. I get all prickly when a service provider tries to get proscriptive about what I should be able to do <em>on my own computer</em>. On geeky principle, I should run the OS and configuration that suits me best. The service provider should implement standards so they don&rsquo;t have to care what I&rsquo;m running. Almost by definition, a service provider that limits what OS you can use, is Doing It Wrong.</p>




<p>Of course that&rsquo;s not the intent here. Take a deep breath, Cam. Microsoft allows you to run anything you like, as long as it&rsquo;s up to date with security patches. Their IT services only <em>support</em> Windows and OSX, but that&rsquo;s not unreasonable. Anyway, the question has come from all sorts of colleagues, not just IT. Deep breaths.</p>




<p>Once I calm my inner Stallman, here are the real reasons:</p>




<ul>
<li><p>I believe that either I own my devices, or they own me. I prefer that <em>I</em> make the decisions about how my computer should work &ndash; especially given what a large proportion of my life is spent working with this thing!</p></li>
<li><p>I trust open source software a lot more than proprietary software. Many eyes make better quality code, and better engineering under the hood.</p></li>
<li><p>It drives me crazy when something goes wrong with a proprietary product. There&rsquo;s usually no way to figure out the problem, know what I can do to improve it, or even how to report it appropriately. It&rsquo;s a black box of frustration.</p></li>
<li><p>I believe that open source software exerts a strong equalizing force on the world. I &ldquo;vote with my behavior&rdquo; to support it.</p></li>
</ul>




<p>In general, as more and more of our lives become computer controlled &ndash; today every car, airplane, pacemaker, and TV are computer-controlled &ndash; it becomes increasingly important that software is open. Given the chance, Google hearing aids would inject advertising into your dinner conversation, while Facebook would block sounds from companies that don&rsquo;t pay. Internet providers have recently won the right to tamper with your content, injecting ads, slowing competitors, and prioritizing their own websites. <strong>I believe that the best tools are controlled by their users.</strong> Open source is how we make that happen.</p>




<p>All these points seem pretty abstract, and they are. But they boil down to a very concrete impression for me: I am used to a computing experience where I am in control, and my device is a neutral extension of myself. So when I use a computer with an OS that someone else has dictated, it&rsquo;s very frustrating! I&rsquo;m frustrated by the ads that I can&rsquo;t block, the buttons that seem to be in the wrong place, the capabilities that are disabled because of someone elses priorities. It makes me feel like I&rsquo;m getting screwed. If your computer doesn&rsquo;t let you watch a region-coded DVD (Windows and OSX), you&rsquo;re getting screwed. If your phone doesn&rsquo;t let you block ads (unrooted IOS and Android), you&rsquo;re getting screwed. If your office suite restricts functionality based on what web browser you&rsquo;re using (Google Apps), you&rsquo;re getting screwed. <strong>I don&rsquo;t like to get screwed</strong>.</p>




<p>So, why do I insist on using open source software whenever possible? Because I feel screwed by proprietary consumer software.</p>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My War on Systemd-resolved]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2018/01/25/my-war-on-systemd-resolved/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-25T11:05:31+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2018/01/25/my-war-on-systemd-resolved</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I run ubuntu as the base for my daily driver machine &ndash; heavily customized though it is &ndash; because Canonical&rsquo;s choices are, by definition, mainstream. That makes them easy to support, easy to understand, and generally easy to work with. So what I&rsquo;m about to describe is exceptional in how frustrating it is for me. Seriously, this one issue keeps is enough to drive me into the arms of another distro.</p>




<p>Ubuntu has a built in DNS cache, which it checks first when trying to resolve anything. This Makes Sense For The User in that DNS queries are resolved faster if they come from local cache. It Makes Sense for the network admin, in that repetitive DNS queries don&rsquo;t take up bandwidth. But it really <strong>doesn&rsquo;t</strong> Make Sense for the web developer.</p>




<p>The local DNS cache takes up port 53, which is a problem if you&rsquo;re trying to run any different kind of DNS service locally. For example, the DNS service that practically any integrated docker-based development environment (<a href="https://docksal.io/">docksal</a>, <a href="https://github.com/drud/ddev#ddev">ddev</a>, <a href="https://docs.amazee.io/local_docker_development/pygmy.html">pygmy</a>, etc etc etc) needs. Even my own haproxy-based setup needs to control DNS. Not to mention, <a href="https://superuser.com/questions/1153203/ubuntu-17-04-systemd-resolved-dns-lookups-randomly-fail">the system randomly fails</a> all on its own! So: in order to do my job, I need to disable the Ubuntu DNS proxy. That&rsquo;s where the trouble begins.</p>




<p>There are a hundred variations on <a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/898605/how-to-disable-systemd-resolved-and-resolve-dns-with-dnsmasq">how to disable systemd-resolvd</a> on askubuntu and stackoverflow. All of them have different suggestions. Partly this is just the flexibility of *nix systems. But it&rsquo;s largely because in the 5 years since Ubuntu introduced the local DNS cache, it&rsquo;s changed which system it&rsquo;s using (twice), how it starts up, how its config is stored, and the overall startup daemon control process. Every year, there are new tricks to learn for how to disable this totally extraneous system. And every time you update, it is magically re-enabled (or enabled in a new way). This is enough that it&rsquo;s kept me from bothering with dist-upgrades for the last year. So I run the latest kernel version, but an old version of the OS, partly because I really hate fighting this problem.</p>




<p>For my own notes, and hopefully to help some others, here is how I disable the local DNS cache on Ubuntu 17.04.</p>


<p><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'># confirm that it&rsquo;s running
</span><span class='line'>$ sudo netstat -tulpn |grep 53
</span><span class='line'>udp        0      0 127.0.0.53:53           0.0.0.0:*                           28168/systemd-resolved
</span><span class='line'>$ sudo ps -aux |grep resolved
</span><span class='line'>systemd+ 28168  0.0  0.0  50024  5300 ?        Ss   Jan24   0:01 /lib/systemd/systemd-resolved
</span><span class='line'># try to kill it.
</span><span class='line'>$ sudo killall systemd-resolved
</span><span class='line'>$ ps -aux |grep resolved
</span><span class='line'>systemd+ 28168  0.0  0.0  50024  5300 ?        Ss   Jan24   0:01 /lib/systemd/systemd-resolved
</span><span class='line'># roll your eyes, and try to disable it through the normal startup routes.
</span><span class='line'>$ sudo service resolvconf disable-updates
</span><span class='line'>$ sudo update-rc.d resolvconf disable
</span><span class='line'>$ sudo service resolvconf stop
</span><span class='line'># pray that it survives a reboot.</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></p>

<p></p>




<p>Note that if you do this, you have to manage your own nameservers in /etc/resolved.conf! In my case networkmanager does it for me, but that won&rsquo;t be true for everyone.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[That Time I Resurrected My Linux MacBook Pro]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2017/06/17/that-time-i-resurrected-my-linux-macbook-pro/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-17T23:06:02+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2017/06/17/that-time-i-resurrected-my-linux-macbook-pro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the airport last week, my laptop stopped booting.</p>

<p>I have a 2012 Macbook Pro &ndash; yes, that coveted &ldquo;last good model&rdquo; &ndash; and it runs Ubuntu Linux. It&rsquo;s my roving office as I travel the world to conferences, performances, and job sites. So when I started it up at JFK airport this week and got a gray screen of death, I was a little concerned.</p>

<p>I tried starting into Startup Manager by holding the &ldquo;Option&rdquo; key. No bootable options appeared. Just an unhopeful file folder with a question mark. This was Not A Good Sign.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/folder-questionmark.jpg" title="When this is all your computer does, it is Not A Good Sign." ></p>

<p>Generally this icon means that EFI couldn&rsquo;t find a valid startup device. This is not the first time I&rsquo;ve seen this &ndash; I&rsquo;ve played with my boot options enough to mess this up for myself a few times! I breathed a heavy sigh and tried starting onto the recovery partition by holding &ldquo;Command+R&rdquo;. I hadn&rsquo;t done anything in particular with Grub recently, but I had done some kernel updates, and you never know&hellip; But the recovery boot just got me a circle with a line through it, the universal &ldquo;no&rdquo; sign. This was an even worse sign.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/mac-no-sign.png" title="This is an Even Worse Sign." ></p>

<p>This immediately threw the issue out of the realm of &ldquo;something I messed up myself&rdquo;, and into the less-entertaining realm of &ldquo;hardware failure.&rdquo;</p>

<p>At home I have some tools for diagnosing this sort of issue, but in the airport I had limited options &ndash; and unlimited time. So I started into Apple&rsquo;s built in Diagnostic Test mode by holding &ldquo;D&rdquo;. A lesser-known feature of the Apple boot manager, is that if it doesn&rsquo;t have a device to boot from, it can download an image from the Internet, load it into RAM, and boot from there. I had never had the chance to try it out before, but that didn&rsquo;t give much satisfaction as I grimly waited for it to work it&rsquo;s magic.</p>

<p>The diagnostic report looked fine, everything in tip-top shape! That is, until I went to the hard drive diagnostic page &ndash; there wasn&rsquo;t one. Not just no hard drive diagnostic, but completely no page for SATA diagnostics at all.</p>

<p>At this point it was clear that a catastrophic hard disk failure was my best-case scenario. Maybe it just skipped the drive diagnostic because no devices reported back, I hoped. There&rsquo;s something zen in that moment, when you find yourself <em>hoping</em> that you&rsquo;ve <em>only</em> lost your entire hard drive. All my work is backed up and relatively accessible, after all; I could stare digital death in the eye with only a hundred-Euro bill for a new drive. A motherboard failure, though &ndash; I tried not to think of it.</p>

<p>When I got home, I pulled out my toolkit. I opened up my mac to look for signs of burnout or other damage. Nothing. No smell, no scorches, no scratches. Not even any capacitor whine. I have a lot of respect for the engineers who designed a system that, even after 5 years of hard abuse, still retained it&rsquo;s &ldquo;new motherboard smell.&rdquo; I optimistically tried re-seating the SATA cable for my drive, but wasn&rsquo;t surprised when that didn&rsquo;t work.</p>

<p>I opened my desktop gaming computer, and plugged my laptop hard disk in there. I got the worst result possible from this test: the drive worked fine. It booted into my beautifully customized Linux desktop, dutifully selecting a random background image from the Internet &ndash; as luck would have it, a man screaming at his laptop in frustration. Though everyone knows that the silicon gods have a strong sense of irony.</p>

<p>I did a couple of follow up tests to confirm the diagnosis, but it was clear: the hard drive was fine, it was the SATA controller on my Macbook that had died. Everything else seemed intact; I could boot from a USB stick just fine, with a reasonable performance degradation (there&rsquo;s a ~33% speed difference between SATA3 and USB3 interfaces). But it couldn&rsquo;t detect anything connected internally.</p>

<p>The first goal was to get myself a computer for work. I&rsquo;m a contractor, which means that I don&rsquo;t take days off if I can help it. So I threw together a nice looking machine from spare parts I had laying around the house, and used my ex-laptop hard drive as a primary. When it first booted, I confess to a very satisfying &ldquo;I told you those parts would come in handy someday&rdquo; jab to my wife. She was very impressed, I could tell from the way she rolled her eyes at me. :)</p>

<p>My immediate need of a working machine for the office satisfied, the second priority was to buy a new laptop. I&rsquo;m on the road <strong>a lot</strong>. A desktop working environment &ndash; even one that lets me cheerfully tease my partner a little &ndash; is a band-aid at best. In fact, my next onsite was in Zürich in two weeks! I briefly considered taking my tower carry-on, before buckling down to find a computer.</p>

<p>My local electronics shop was a bust. They had plenty of beautiful looking machines that would run Linux perfectly nicely &ndash; those Lenovos are really coming along! &ndash; but they all had one fatal flaw: I can&rsquo;t work on a German keyboard.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve lived in Germany for 6 years now; I&rsquo;m comfortable in the language and culture, and I can complain about the bureaucracy with the best of them. But I just can&rsquo;t handle their terrible keyboard layout. QWERTZ might be fine for writing the language, but code and the *nix terminal are very QWERTY-centric. No, there was no way I would put up with a QWERTZ laptop for my next 5 years.</p>

<p>So I bought one of the popular Dell XPS 13 &ldquo;developer edition&rdquo; laptops, with Ubuntu pre-installed. I excitedly checked my order status right away, and saw the shipping date&hellip; was the day after I leave for Zürich. Shit.</p>

<p>So my old laptop is back in service, limping along for one last hurrah. The black box on the back looks like some impressive hardware hack, but it&rsquo;s just the old internal drive connected by USB.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/me-and-my-busted-laptop.jpg" title="It&rsquo;s only a flesh wound!" ></p>

<p>Yes, I had to do the GRUB dance pretty extensively to get it booting. boot-repair is a wonderful tool, but nothing seems to handle elegantly switching between BIOS and EFI boot modes. I ended up having to copy EFI files from my USB stick by hand. As every Linux desktop user ever has said: &ldquo;if it&rsquo;s working I won&rsquo;t ask any questions.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Yes, I will take this computer into a board room in two weeks.</p>

<p>No, I am not ashamed. I&rsquo;m actually pretty satisfied with myself. It&rsquo;s been years since I&rsquo;ve built a computer myself, let alone rigged one up with duct tape and spare parts. It&rsquo;s been ages since I&rsquo;ve had to dig around in the Linux boot process (greatly improved since 2005, Linus be praised). And it&rsquo;s been a long time since I&rsquo;ve sported duct tape on my computer.</p>

<p>In a couple weeks I&rsquo;ll find out just how much special sauce Dell has put into their default Ubuntu setup to make it run. My setup is&hellip; not very default.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Perfect Linux Mint on My Macbook Pro 9,2]]></title>
    <link href="http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2016/10/15/perfect-linux-mint-macbook-pro-9-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-15T18:44:40+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://ohthehugemanatee.org/blog/2016/10/15/perfect-linux-mint-macbook-pro-9-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few months ago I posted about my <a href="/blog/2015/10/01/how-i-got-el-capitain-working-with-my-developer-tools/">frustrations getting El Capitan working</a> with my relatively simple developer needs. At the time I complained about the direction Apple is going. One of these days, I threatened, I would jump back to Linux as a primary desktop environment.</p>

<p>This week I read about everyone&rsquo;s problems getting OSX Sierra going, and I decided it was time to take the plunge. Apple, I completely understand the direction you are going with your environment. You&rsquo;ve gotta lock down in order to make peoples' computers reliable, easy to use appliances. But I don&rsquo;t want an appliance, I want a computer. I disagree with some of your choices about the system, what software I should use, where I may install it from, and how I may use it. I&rsquo;m switching to an OS that lets me make those choices.</p>

<p>Someone recently described the choice to me as &ldquo;program, or be programmed.&rdquo; That really stuck in my mind. OSX increasingly feels like &ldquo;someone else&rsquo;s computer&rdquo; for me. Someone else is making all the choices. Well, I don&rsquo;t have to &ldquo;be programmed&rdquo; passively. I can run an environment which respects my choices about privacy, which gives me the freedom to do whatever I want with my computer. So this week I went back to Linux.</p>

<p>The last time I used Linux as a primary laptop OS was with Gentoo in 2003. OK, easy to say that this has come a LONG way since then. Still I don&rsquo;t know if I would recommend converting your existing system if you&rsquo;re a techno noob; better to buy a system with Linux pre-configured. With that said, I am damn impressed with how well <a href="http://linuxmint.com/">Linux Mint</a> runs out of the box on my Macbook Pro 9,2 (mid-2012). Setting everything up was a snap.</p>

<h2>How to Get Linux Mint 18 running perfectly on a Macbook Pro 9,2</h2>

<p>Just install it. Seriously, that&rsquo;s it. It just works.TM</p>

<p>Installation went totally smoothly for me. I am dual booting for now, but I haven&rsquo;t had to get back into OSX all week. Note that you can access all your OSX files from inside Linux, as long as you don&rsquo;t have OSX&rsquo;s &ldquo;FileVault&rdquo; disk encryption turned on. Only Macs can decrypt that. There is a similar (more compatible) full disk encryption system for Linux, but at least during the transition I advise you to disable encryption for both &ldquo;sides&rdquo; of your computer. I did have to install ReFind to keep the dual boot working.</p>

<p>Linux Mint asks you for permission to use the non-GPL drivers it needs to run your wireless card, and your CPU&rsquo;s special capabilities. It was a checkbox. Everything just worked. I really tried to find anything substantially broken out of the box, and came up empty. Touchpad, sound, webcam, suspend/resume&hellip; everything worked just fine.</p>

<h2>Applications</h2>

<p>I was pleasantly surprised to find that all of my most important applications have Linux flavors available, and they&rsquo;re easy to install. Much easier &ndash; or more standardized at least &ndash; than installation packages on OSX or Windows! Here are the big ones I use, with any relevant notes.</p>

<ul>
<li>SimpleNote</li>
<li>Firefox Developer Edition</li>
<li>PHPStorm &ndash; sadly I couldn&rsquo;t get it to keep my old licenses. I had to re-enter my license code manually.</li>
<li>Toggl</li>
<li>PrivateInternetAccess</li>
<li>Slack &ndash; this app is pretty slow, surprisingly. I may go back to the web version.</li>
<li>Zoom meetings &ndash; still just as painful on Linux</li>
<li>Skype &ndash; skype.com has a newer version of this than the apt repo. No idea what the difference is, but it&rsquo;s still a resource hog.</li>
<li>Lastpass &ndash; browser extension, but deserves a special mention. The version of the extension that&rsquo;s installed automatically (3.3.1) is SLOW and could never connect to Lastpass reliably. Did I mention it&rsquo;s SLOW? It singlehandedly destroyed my system&rsquo;s performance. Visit <a href="">the extension&rsquo;s page on addons.mozilla.org</a> and scroll down down down until you find &ldquo;developer channel&rdquo;. There you can download the current version, 4.1.29a. That&rsquo;s fast and light and current and working.</li>
<li>FileVault &ndash; I keep my most sensitive files in a filevault-encrypted image. Unfortunately, only macs can open that format. I moved everything into a Veracrypt encrypted image instead, as the best multi-platform option.</li>
<li>Docker &ndash; docker &ldquo;native&rdquo; for mac is actually running on a very slim Linux VM, so I knew it would be faster on a native Linux machine. But I was surprised that my informal benchmarks clocked it at almost 3x faster!</li>
</ul>


<p>I was worried about application coverage, but so far I haven&rsquo;t found any gaps.</p>

<h2>Tweaks</h2>

<p>I had two big tweaks: the task bar, and the touchpad. I also did one minor tweak to improve my battery life.</p>

<p>I actually like the OSX dock and task bar concept. I find the default Windows-style taskbar finicky and a painful way to describe what applications are currently running. So I added <a href="https://glx-dock.org/">Cairo Dock</a>, and configured Cinnamon&rsquo;s built in taskbars to be a bit more OSX'ish.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m very finicky about my touchpad&rsquo;s behavior, and Linux Mint&rsquo;s control panel didn&rsquo;t expose enough of the options to me. Fortunately the Mac touchpad runs on the excellent <a href="ftp://www.x.org/pub/X11R7.5/doc/man/man4/synaptics.4.html">Synaptics driver</a>. That means you can configure every detail from the terminal with &ldquo;synclient optionname=value&rdquo; or &ldquo;synclient -l&rdquo; to list your current settings. Use that man page I linked to tell what options do what, and you can set the perfect configuration. Once you&rsquo;ve figured out what options are just right for you, put them in a file called /etc/X11/xorg.conf.d/60-synaptics.conf, like this:</p>

<p><code>
Section "InputClass"
  Identifier "touchpad"
  Driver "synaptics"
  MatchIsTouchpad "on"
  MatchDevicePath "/dev/input/event*"
  Option "FingerHigh" "90"
  Option "CoastingSpeed" "7"
  Option "CoastingFriction" "16"
  Option "EmulateTwoFingerMinW" "2"
  Option "RTCornerButton" "0"
  Option "RBCornerButton" "0"
  Option "LTCornerButton" "0"
  Option "LBCornerButton" "0"
  Option "PalmDetect" "on"
EndSection
</code></p>

<p>You will probably have to create the xorg.conf.d subdirectory&hellip; and you&rsquo;ll have to be sudo for the whole thing.</p>

<p>Finally, I thought I&rsquo;d try to get more life out of this old battery. So I installed <a href="https://01.org/powertop">powertop</a>, and accepted all of it&rsquo;s automated recommendations. Now I get about 5 hours, which matches my experience in OSX. It is a 4 year old laptop, after all!</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it. One file to edit from the terminal, press &ldquo;OK&rdquo; a bunch on one application, and I got (what feels to me) like a perfect setup. This is so much better than the old days of walking uphill through the snow (both ways!) to get your display working. This is a polished, pleasant to use desktop environment.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m happy I switched.</p>

<p>Update October 17 &ndash; The hardware CPU fan governor was letting the CPU run very very hot. I finally installed <a href="https://github.com/dgraziotin/mbpfan">mbpfan</a>, and it&rsquo;s under control again. This is all just&hellip; so much more painless than I remember!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
